Emile Berliner Collection
Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division, Library of Congress
Emile Berliner collection 1871-1965 1871-1930
Berliner, Emile, 1851-1929
41 boxes (approximately 1,000 items)
232 photographic prints: black and white, 1 color; 10 x 13 inches and smaller
29 negatives: black and white; 8 x 10 inches and smaller
over 400 sound discs, including zinc, copper, celluloid, rubber, shellac, and vinyl pressings and masters, in various speeds, and in sizes ranging from 5 to 12 inches in diameter
1 film reel of 1 (12 feet): silent, black-and-white; 16 mm. nitrate
over 100 items, chiefly telephone, gramophone, and laboratory equipment, with 7 acoustic insulating panels and material samples, all made of various materials and in various sizes
Recorded Sound Reference Center, Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Unpublished and published textual materials, photographs, sound recordings, scrapbooks, artifacts, and a motion picture documenting the life and work of the German-born immigrant to America who invented the gramophone, the flat disc recording, the radio microphone, acoustic tile, and an early version of the helicopter. Included are unpublished and experimental gramophone records dating from the 1890s, some of them featuring the voices of Berliner and various family members, as well as recordings published by Berliner's gramophone companies in the U.S., Canada, and Germany.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Allen, Roy Morris, 1882- --Correspondence.; Bell, Alexander Graham, 1847-1922.; Berliner family.; Berliner, Cora A., 1862-1942--Photographs.; Berliner, Emile, 1851-1929--Archives.; Berliner, Emile, 1851-1929--Correspondence.; Berliner, Emile, 1851-1929--Photographs.; Berliner, Emile, 1851-1929--Trials. litigation, etc.; Berliner, Emile, 1851-1929.; Berliner, Emile, 1851-1929. Muddy Jim, and other rhymes.; Berliner, Jacob, 1849-1918--Correspondence.; Hyatt, John W. (John Wesley), 1837-1920--Correspondence.; Richards, W. L. (William L.)--Correspondence.; Sanders, Joseph, 1877-1960.
Organizations
American Bell Telephone Company.; American Telephone and Telegraph Company.; Berliner (Record company)
Subjects
Acoustical engineering--United States.; Acoustical materials.; Architectural acoustics.; German Americans--Washington (D.C.)--Archives.; Ghost dance.; Health education--United States.; Immigrants--Washington (D.C.)--Archives.; Inventions.; Jews--Washington (D.C.)--Archives.; Microphone.; Milk--Pasteurization.; Patent suits--United States.; Patents--Germany.; Patents--United States.; Phonograph--United States.; Popular music--United States--To 1901.; Public health--United States.; Sound recordings--United States.; Sound recordings.; Sound--Experiments.; Sound--Recording and reproducing--Equipment and supplies.; Sound--Recording and reproducing--United States.; Sound--Recording and reproducing.; Telephone--Experiments.; Telephone--United States.; Zionism--United States.
Form/Genre
Acoustic equipment.; Awards.; Books.; Clippings (Information artifacts); Correspondence.; Diaries.; Journals (Accounts); Memorandums.; Pamphlets.; Patents.; Phonograph records.; Photographs.; Portrait photographs.; Research notes.; Scrapbooks.; Sound recordings.; Speeches.; Test pressings (Sound recordings); Trade catalogs.
Occupations
Health reformers--United States.; Inventors--United States.
Administrative Information
Collection Acquisition
Several of Emile Berliner's descendants, including Robert Sanders, Mrs. Robert (Emily) Sanders, Robert Frank, and Joseph Sanders, have donated materials to the collection, or in some cases, loaned materials to the Library of Congress for duplication, from 1979 through 1992. Additional items have been added through Library purchases.
Additions
No further additions to the collection are expected.
Access Restrictions
The Emile Berliner Collection is open for research. Advance notice may be required; contact a reference librarian in the Recorded Sound Reference Center, Library of Congress, Washington, DC, 20540-4690; (202) 707-7833.
The artifacts and early unpublished sound discs that are included in the collection are not yet available to researchers. After processing and preservation has been completed, the materials will be accessible through a revised version of this finding aid and the Library of Congress Online Catalog.
Online Content
Selected sound recordings, photographs, textual materials (such as articles, speeches, notes, and scrapbooks), artifacts, and a film from the collection are available in digital form on the Library of Congress website under the title: "Emile Berliner and the Birth of the Recording Industry" at http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/berlhtml/berlhome.html Links to the digitized items are also provided in the container list of this finding aid.
Related Material
Additional Emile Berliner papers are located in the Manuscript Division of the Library of Congress.
Biographical Note
Emile Berliner (1851-1929) was a prominent inventor living at the end of the nineteenth and the beginning of the twentieth centuries. Overlooked by today's historians, Berliner's creative genius rivaled that of his better-known contemporaries Thomas Alva Edison and Alexander Graham Bell, and, like the works of these two inventors, Berliner's innovations helped shape the modern American way of life. Although Berliner did not invent recorded sound technology, his innovations led to its mass distribution. His flat-disc recordings eventually replaced the more fragile and unwieldy Edison cylinders as consumers' sound technology of choice.
Emile (originally Emil) Berliner was born in Hanover, Germany, on May 20, 1851. He was one of thirteen children born to Samuel and Sarah Fridman Berliner, two of whom died in infancy. His father was a merchant and a Talmudic scholar, and his mother was an amateur musician.
Following a few years of school in Hanover, Berliner was sent to nearby Wolfenbüttel to attend the Samsonschule from which he graduated in 1865 at the age of fourteen. This marked the end of his formal schooling and Berliner then spent several years at odd jobs in Hanover helping to support the large Berliner family. Enticed by the offer of a clerkship in a store partly owned by a man named Behrend, a Hanoverian who had emigrated to the United States some time earlier, and perhaps by a desire to escape the military duty that faced most young men in the year of the Franco-Prussian War, Berliner persuaded his parents to allow him to accept the job offer and to emigrate to America. In late March 1870 he left Hanover.
The dry-goods store was located in Washington, D.C. For three years Berliner clerked for Gotthelf, Behrend and Co. until in 1873 he decided a better opportunity awaited him in New York City. There Berliner again took up onerous jobs during the day while trying to improve himself by studying privately at night at the Cooper Institute. After a brief career as a "drummer" (traveling salesman) for a "gents' furnishings" (men's clothing and accessories) establishment in Milwaukee, Berliner again went back to New York where this time he was most fortunate in obtaining a position as general cleanup man in the laboratory of Constantine Fahlberg, the discoverer of saccharine. This experience in a research laboratory fired Berliner's ambition, and he decided that science, research, and invention were to be his destiny.
In 1876 Berliner returned to what was now Behrend and Co. in Washington and resumed his clerkship. That was the year of the American centennial celebrations, and among the outstanding events that took place in Washington was a demonstration of the new telephone of Alexander Graham Bell. Berliner saw the instrument for the first time and was filled with enthusiasm. He commenced to study the telephone. To his inquiring mind one of the instrument's weaknesses was its transmitter. Working alone in his rooming house he fashioned a new type of transmitter which he called a "loose-contact" transmitter, a type of microphone, which increased the volume of the transmitted voice. When the members of the newly-formed American Bell Telephone Company were advised that a young and entirely unknown man in Washington had submitted a caveat (Berliner wrote it himself without the aid of a patent attorney) to the Patent Office covering a new transmitter, they could hardly believe it. Thomas Watson, the Mr. Watson of telephone fame, was sent to Washington to make inquiries. He returned such a glowing report of the transmitter and of Berliner himself that the company offered to buy the rights to the invention and to hire Berliner as a research assistant. For the next seven years, Berliner was employed by the ABT Co., first in New York City and then in Boston. During those years Berliner worked on numerous problems associated with the fledgling telephone industry and developed into a first-class theoretical electrician.
While working in Boston in 1881, Berliner became an American citizen and in the same year married a young woman of German descent named Cora Adler. In 1884 Berliner decided to set himself up as a private researcher and inventor, his cherished dream. He resigned from the American Bell Telephone Company and he and Cora left Boston and set up housekeeping in Washington, D.C. The Berliners had six children, Edgar, Herbert, Henry, Louise, Hannah and Alice.
In Washington, Berliner began working on additional improvements to Bell's telephone, selling the rights to his patents to the telephone company. Then in 1886 he began working on the invention that was to prove his most important contribution to the world. This was the development of the gramophone, the recording and reproduction of sound by means of disc records. Among his other inventions were:
Floor Covering
As early as 1883, while still working for the telephone company, Berliner obtained Patent 284,268 for a new type of floor covering which he termed Parquet Carpet. From time to time he returned to this work and he obtained additional Patents 621,316 in 1899 and 656,162 in 1900.
Acoustic Tile
As one who frequently attended orchestral concerts, operas, and other musical events, as well as lectures, plays, and sermons, Berliner was well aware of the poor acoustics of many halls, theaters, churches, and synagogues. Having studied acoustics for many years, he decided to do something about the situation. He soon came up with a new type of tile that could be affixed to the existing walls of rooms. Acoustic tiles were, in the inventor's words, "... composed of porous cement, are as hard as stone, and yet have the resonance of wood when vibrated by a tuning fork."
In 1926 he obtained Patent 1,573,475 for these tiles. They were eminently successful in the days before public address systems. Among the buildings that added these tiles were the auditorium of Drexel University in Philadelphia, Stanley Theater in Jersey City, the Church of the Messiah in Montreal, Leicester Theatre in London, Uptown Theater in Philadelphia, the Second Presbyterian Church in Pittsburgh, and the board room of the Karachi Port Trust in what is now Pakistan.
The Helicopter and the Lightweight Internal Combustion Engine
In 1906 or 1907 Emile Berliner became fascinated with the possibilities of the flying machine. This led to his involvement in the development of the helicopter which, as he himself said, was one of the earliest forms of heavier-than-air machines conceived, going back at least as far as the time of Leonardo da Vinci. Berliner designed and patented a new type of lightweight internal combustion engine to power the rotors. By 1909 he had constructed a working model that was capable of lifting the weight of two adult men, however the helicopter was tethered to the ground and no free flight was attempted. Although Berliner had to relinquish his work on the helicopter, his son Henry continued it.
Emile Berliner for many years took an active role in community and social causes, particularly in the public health field. In 1909 he donated funds for an infirmary building at the Starmont Tuberculosis Sanitarium in Washington Grove, Maryland, dedicated to the memory of his father. Berliner was president of the Washington Tuberculosis Association for some years. In 1924, he inaugurated the Bureau of Health Education to promote public hygiene and health education for mothers and children.
The subject of children's health was close to his heart. In 1900 his youngest daughter, Alice, became desperately ill, very likely from bacteria picked up from some food or drink. Because of this illness Berliner campaigned against the high mortality rate of babies and young children. He became a fervent advocate of clean milk and by all means at his disposal he preached to mothers to "scald the milk" before serving it. He also became disgusted by what he perceived to be the neglect of cleanliness in children. In 1919 he and some of his associates wrote and published a book of colored drawings with accompanying rhymes illustrating what happens to children who neglect cleanliness. Entitled Muddy Jim, the book was given to schools in the Washington area and elsewhere. All the rhymes were written by Emile Berliner. The book was soon translated into French, possibly for distribution in the Canadian province of Quebec.
Zionism was another cause that involved Emile Berliner deeply. Between 1913 and 1918, Berliner wrote four articles on the subject: "The Social Status of the Jews," "Zionism and the American Spirit," "Americanism and Zionism," and "Thoughts on Zionism." In 1919 Berliner was named chairman of the Committee on Arrangements for a reception for the celebrated rabbi Stephen S. Wise. During the same year he wrote a letter to the editors of both the Washington Star and the Washington Post concerning the second commemoration of the 1917 declaration by British statesman Arthur Balfour that "His Majesty's Government favors establishment of a national home for the Jews in Palestine." In 1919, Berliner wrote another article on "A Study Towards the Solution of Industrial Problems in the New Zionist Commonwealth."
Berliner inherited a great fondness for music from his mother and was an avid concert-goer. That he could play the piano is attested by one of his assistants in the gramophone laboratory who said that Berliner was the pianist on some of the very early recordings. In 1897 he wrote a song entitled "Columbian Anthem" in honor of the nation's capital, the District of Columbia. It was arranged for male quartet and was recorded in 1897 on Berliner record 4288 and seems to have been re-recorded several times before June 1900.
In addition to his contributions to the progress of recorded sound, Emile Berliner worked tirelessly in many other endeavors both business-related and philanthropic. His development of microphone and recorded sound technology remains, however, the greater part of his legacy. His work on microphones was so successful that it replaced the earlier microphone used by Alexander Graham Bell for his telephone systems. It is still the basic design used in most microphones manufactured today. His flat-disc design for the gramophone has became the standard for mass-produced commercial sound recordings and was the precursor of today's digital compact discs.
Emile Berliner died on August 3, 1929, in his seventy-ninth year.
Scope and Content Note
The Emile Berliner Collection includes disc recordings, textual materials, photographs, artifacts, and a film. The textual materials consist of more than 1,000 items including correspondence, notes and papers, books, addresses, newspaper and magazine articles, catalogs, diaries and journals, pamphlets, patents, and scrapbooks dealing with Berliner's work and personal life, as well as his philanthropic endeavors. The photographs are both studio portraits and informal snapshots of Berliner, his family, his associates, and his inventions. Artifacts include telephone, gramophone, and laboratory equipment, along with several acoustic panel pieces and material samples.
The recorded sound component of the Berliner Collection consists of unpublished zinc records, some of them experimental (1892-1898); unpublished discs made of various materials for both experimental and private uses; and published celluloid, rubber, and shellac Berliner Gramophone Company pressings made in the United States (pre-1900), Canada, and Germany (pre- and post-1900). The published records represent one of the first successful attempts to mass-market and commercially distribute popular sound recordings. Some of the unpublished discs in the collection feature the voices of Berliner and various family members. Also available are post-1900 Victor records; 78 rpm records published by other companies; and several vinyl LP recordings.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 17 series:
Series 1: Addresses, 1888-1929, undated
Series 2: Journal Articles and Newspaper Clippings, 1883, 1900, 1922, 1927-1929, 1955
Series 3: Artifacts, undated
Series 4: Books, 1879-1928
Series 5: Catalogs, 1895-1896
Series 6: Correspondence, 1871-1926, 1946, 1955
Series 7: Journals and Diaries, 1889-1907
Series 8: Miscellaneous Materials, 1897-1929
Series 9: Notes and Papers, 1877-1928
Series 10: Pamphlets, 1890-1929, 1951, undated
Series 11: Patents, 1879-1909
Series 12: Photographs, 1871-1965, undated
Series 13: Sound Recordings, circa 1890-1950s
Series 14: Scrapbooks, 1885-1930
Series 15: Joseph Sanders Materials, 1896-1927, 1953-1955
Series 16: Acoustic Tile, 1899, 1925-1929
Series 17: Film, 1904
http://lccn.loc.gov/2011622951
Container List
- Series 1. Addresses, circa 1888-1929, .5 linear feet
  Series 1 contains copies of speeches and addresses by Emile Berliner on a variety of subjects. Examples include a 1888 speech delivered to the Franklin Institute on the gramophone, a 1925 paper prepared for the D.C. chapter of the American Institute of Architects on acoustic tiles, and three addresses on transmitters and the development of the talking machine. It also includes an address by Berliner from 1913 for the National Farm School on the social status of the Jews.
  - 1888-1929 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - 1888-1929 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - 1888-1929 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - 1913 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - circa 1925 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - 1929 (Box-folder 1/6)
- Series 2. Journal Articles and Newspaper Clippings, 1883, 1900, 1922, 1927-1929, 1955, 1 linear foot
  Series 2 consists of journal articles and newspaper clippings which chronicle Berliners life, interests and inventions, the bulk of which are obituaries from 1929. Some early articles focus on Berliner's inventions of the gramophone, microphone, and acoustic improvements. Later articles highlight his efforts on health care and curing infant mortality. Journals include Young Israel, the American Hebrew, and Journal of Outdoor Life. Newspapers include the New York Times, the Washington Post, the Washington Herald, the Philadelphia Evening Public Ledger, the Evening Post, and the Philadelphia Inquirer, among others.
  - Articles on the gramophone, 1922-1955 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Articles on the gramophone, 1900, 1952 (Box-folder OS1/1)
  - Articles on the telephone, microphone, 1922-1955 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Articles on the telephone, microphone, 1883 (Box-folder OS1/2)
  - Articles and clippings on health, 1922-1955 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Newspaper clippings on health, 1928-1929 (Box-folder OS1/3)
  - Articles on acoustic tile, 1922-1955 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Newspaper clippings on acoustic tile, 1928 (Box-folder OS1/4)
  - Biographical and miscellaneous articles, 1922-1955 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Newspaper clippings on Berliner's death, 1929 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Newspaper clippings on Berliner's death, 1929 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Newspaper clippings on Berliner's death, 1929 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Newspaper clippings on Berliner's death, 1929 (Box-folder OS1/5)
  - Newspaper clippings on Berliner's death and other topics, 1929 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Miscellaneous articles, 1922-1955 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings, undated (Box-folder OS1/6)
- Series 3. Artifacts, undated, .5 linear feet
  This series holds actual parts from machines. They include talking machine needles and washers.
  - Sprechmaschinen-nandeln [Talking machine needles], undated (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Washer samples, undated (Box-folder 4/2)
- Series 4. Books, 1879-1928, 3.5 linear feet
  This series consists of 23 books and includes court proceedings, arguments, briefs, and affidavits for Berliner’s court cases (U.S. v. American Bell Telephone Co. and Emile Berliner, bound issues of the serial Telegraphic Journal and Electrical Review, v. VIII, and many copies of Muddy Jim and Other Rhymes, a book written by Berliner on children’s health issues. This series also includes the supplement to Muddy Jim written by Dr. George M. Kober, professor of hygiene at Georgetown University, and a copy of A bas les maladies! published by the Association for the Prevention of Tuberculosis of Washington, D.C.
  - A Bas les Maladies! 1919 (Box-folder 5/1-3)
  - Annual Report of the Smithsonian Board of Regents, 1908 (Box-folder 5/5)
  - United States of America v. American Bell Telephone Co. and Emile Berliner, brief for defendants, 1894 (Box-folder 5/6)
  - History of the Telephone Transmitter, 1894 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Gedenkblätter 150 Stiftungstag des Wohltätigkeitsverins der Synagogengemeinde Hannover (Pages of testimony in memory of the Foundation Day charities for the synagogue community in Hanover, Germany), 1912 (Box-folder 6/2)
    Annotation on front cover notes the page number of the account of Berliner’s 42 years of service in Jewish charity work.
  - United States of America v. American Bell Telephone Co. and Emile Berliner, brief for defendants, 1894 (Box-folder 6/3-4)
    Two copies.
  - Jubiläumsschrift der Telephon-Fabrik Actiengesellschaft (25th Jubilee Book of the J. Berliner Telephone Factory), 1881-1906 (Box-folder 7/1)
  - Muddy Jim and Other Rhymes, 1919 (Box-folder 7/2)
  - Muddy Jim: Supplement: 12 Chapters in Hygiene, circa 1919 (Box-folder 7/3)
  - Telegraphic Journal and Electrical Review: v. 7, January–December, 1879 (Box-folder 7/4)
  - Twelve Years of the Telephone Pioneers of America, 1923 (Box-folder 7/5)
  - Various Aspects of Birth Control, 1928 (Box-folder 7/6)
  - Washington Health Rules, 1915 (Box-folder 7/7)
  - United States of America v. American Bell Telephone Co. and Emile Berliner, argument of J. J. Storrow, Esq. for defendants, 1894 (Box-folder 8/1)
  - United States of America v. American Bell Telephone Co. and Emile Berliner, argument of J. J. Storrow, Esq. for defendants, 1894 (Box-folder 8/2)
  - United States of America v. American Bell Telephone Co. and Emile Berliner, summary brief for defendants, 1894 (Box-folder 8/3)
  - United States of America v. American Bell Telephone Co. and Emile Berliner, argument of Frederick P. Fish, for defendants, 1893 (Box-folder 8/4)
  - United States of America v. American Bell Telephone Co. and Emile Berliner, v. I, pleadings and evidence, 1894 (Box-folder 8/5)
  - United States of America v. American Bell Telephone Co. and Emile Berliner, v. II, exhibits, 1894 (Box-folder 9/1)
  - American Bell Telephone Co. et al, v. the United States of America, memorandum of points made and references noted in oral argument by counsel for complainant, 1894 (Box-folder 9/2)
  - American Bell Telephone Co., Emile Berliner v. the United States of America, brief for appellants; Appellants reply to appellee’s memorandum; Summary of proceedings, 1895 (Box-folder 9/3)